<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-06T22:26:55-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Home</title><subtitle>Yuemei Liu - Ph.D. candidate at University of Florida</subtitle><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><entry><title type="html">4. Real-time Perceptually-enabled Task Guidance in the Extremes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2022/01/01/DARPA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4. Real-time Perceptually-enabled Task Guidance in the Extremes" /><published>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/markdown/2022/01/01/DARPA</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2022/01/01/DARPA.html"><![CDATA[<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
This a DARPA-funded project on the use of augmented reality for providing knowledge task guidance in extreme situations. The research challenge is to create a data-to-knowledge "pipeline" from wearable devices to an intelligent agency that can determine what information or guidance to provide to human operators in real-time. 
</p>
</font>

<h3 id="41-project-overview">4.1 Project overview</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">

This project is to investigate augmented reality (AR) technologies for providing real-time knowledge-task guidance in extreme environments, including military helicopter pilot checklist completion and Army field-medic care for soldier amputee cases. Research requires application of formal task modeling approaches, including object-action identification with contingency states. User state modeling is to be conducted with real-time physiological measures and machine learning methods for state classification. User models are to be linked to AR interfaces to trigger presentation of task-relevant guidance during high-fidelity simulator trials. Guidance will be based on real-time execution of task simulation models in sync with experiment protocols being performed by actual human operators. Results will be used to support Army applications of AR devices.<br /><br />

My responsibility in this project is to use feature engineering and ML techniques to predict operator cognitive workload based on real-time physiological signals collected by the wearable devices. 

</p>
</font>

<h3 id="42-related-papers">4.2 Related papers</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
In processing...
</p>
</font>

<h3 id="43-demo-video">4.3 Demo video</h3>

<!-- ![](https://youtu.be/6xAK8W69i-g) -->

<p align="center">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6xAK8W69i-g" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>]]></content><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><category term="markdown" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This a DARPA-funded project on the use of augmented reality for providing knowledge task guidance in extreme situations. The research challenge is to create a data-to-knowledge "pipeline" from wearable devices to an intelligent agency that can determine what information or guidance to provide to human operators in real-time.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3. EMG-based Assistive Human-Machine Interface Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/12/01/NSF.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3. EMG-based Assistive Human-Machine Interface Design" /><published>2019-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/12/01/NSF</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/12/01/NSF.html"><![CDATA[<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">This is an NSF-funded project to develop models of powered-prosthetic user cognitive workload when applying different modes of electromyography (EMG)-based device control. Models are to be used for predicting workload associated with use of EMG-based control interfaces in other applications.
</p>
</font>

<h3 id="31-project-overview">3.1 Project overview</h3>

<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
This project is to provide engineering and design guidance for EMG-based assistive human-machine interactions for human performance of basic psychomotor and real-time, high-demand control tasks. To achieve this goal, there are three experiments. Currently we have completed the first experiment, are working on the second experiment, and are preparing for the third experiment.<br /><br />

<b> 1st EXPERIMENT</b><br />

 To identify the differences in cognitive load in using various EMG-based HMIs，first experiment made comparison of direct-control device with EMG-response pattern-recognition control, and continuous control technology. Through two tasks, CRT and SHAP, user performance data, usability evaluations and workload surveys were collected. <br /><br />
<img src="/assets/images/banners/NSF-Phase1.png" />


<br /><br /><b> 2nd EXPERIMENT</b><br />

Second experiment makes assessment of use of EMG-based control interface with virtual reality-based simulation of prosthetic manipulations in activities of daily living. The schematic below shows the hardware setup for the experiment.  <br /><br />
<img src="/assets/images/banners/NSF-Phase2.png" />

<br /><br /><b> 3rd EXPERIMENT</b><br />
Final study will assess driver use of EMG-based control interface to perform basic driving tasks in high fidelity simulator. Work is expected to result in a set of design guidelines for EMG-based control interface designs for various applications. <br /><br />


</p>
</font>

<h3 id="32-related-paper">3.2 Related paper</h3>

<h4 id="submitted-paper">Submitted paper</h4>
<p><b>[C2]</b>. Park, J., Berman, J., Dodson, A., <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Matthew, A., Huang, H., Kaber, D., Ruiz, J., and Zahabi, M. (2022; under review). Cognitive workload classification of upper-limb prosthetic devices, 2022 IEEE 3rd International Conference on Human-Machine Systems (ICHMS), 2022, pp. XX-XX.</p>

<h4 id="working-paper">Working paper</h4>
<p><b>[5]</b>. Park, J., Berman, J., Dodson, A., <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Armstrong, M., Huang, H., Kaber, D., Ruiz, J., and Zahabi, M. (Sep. 2022). Cognitive workload classification of electromyography (EMG)-based prosthetic devices. About to submit to <i>Ergonomics</i>.<br /><br />
 <b>[6]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Park, J., Berman, J., Dodson, A., Huang, H., Kaber, D., Ruiz, J., and Zahabi, M. (Sep. 2022). Human-centered evaluation of EMG-based upper-limb prosthetic control schemes: direct control, pattern recognition control and continuous control. About to submit to IEEE <i>Transactions on Human-Machine Systems</i>.</p>

<!-- ### 3.3 Demo video
![](https://youtu.be/6xAK8W69i-g) -->]]></content><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><category term="markdown" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an NSF-funded project to develop models of powered-prosthetic user cognitive workload when applying different modes of electromyography (EMG)-based device control. Models are to be used for predicting workload associated with use of EMG-based control interfaces in other applications.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1. Research on Automation Rate and Situation Awareness Responses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Dissertation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1. Research on Automation Rate and Situation Awareness Responses" /><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Dissertation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Dissertation.html"><![CDATA[<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
During the operation of automated systems, if a user cannot accurately understand the structure and function of automation of the system, it is likely that distrust or over-trust in the automation will occur. To address this research gap, my dissertation research developed a continuous “automation rate” function to quantify levels of automation in complex  systems. In addition, I proposed a new relationship between the AR function and operator situation awareness responses, based on existing empirical research findings.
</p>
</font>

<h3 id="11-project-overview">1.1 Project overview</h3>

<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">

Many taxonomies of levels of automation for human-in-the-loop systems have been presented in the literature; however, the discrete and ordinal nature of these references limits reliable prediction of operator performance when using various levels of automation. This research defines an “automation rate” to quantify the level of automation for human-in-the-loop systems. The automation rate is calculated as a weighted proportion of systems functions assigned to automation and/or joint human-automation control over the total number of system functions, including those assigned to a human operator. <br /><br />

In addition, this research proposes a new relationship between the system automation rate and operator situation awareness. Based on prior empirical research findings, it was observed that any model of situation awareness in the rate of system automation should account for the level of operator expertise, as well as their attitude towards the use of automation, and should have curve-linear characteristics. Through a model fitting exercise, based on prior meta-analysis results, we found that a scaled-exponential function with shift produced the greatest degree of fit with situation awareness responses. The result represents a hypothesis of the relation of complex system operator situation awareness with the new automation rate quotient. <br /><br />

To demonstrate the effectiveness of the automation rate model and properties of situation awareness response, a case study was conducted. The objects of this case included two types of vehicles with SAE Level 2 LOA, including the Ford Fusion and Tesla Model 3. Picture below visualizes the automation rate for each stage of information processing for each of the two vehicles <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9582630" target="_blank">[C4]</a>.<br /><br />
<img src="/assets/images/banners/Dissertation.png" />

<br /><br />

In order to verify the effectiveness of the automation rate model and its relationship with operator situation awareness, the following study will conduct a laboratory experiment to collect data on driver behavior and situation awareness responses to the use of various levels of vehicle automation applied to driving tasks using a high-fidelity driving simulator. The experiment will test multiple levels of automation ranging from manual control to automated control of both longitudinal and lateral vehicle position for effects on driver situation awareness in various roadway configurations. This data set will be used as a basis for testing the hypothesized relation of the new automation rate model to driver situation awareness responses.
</p>
</font>

<h3 id="12-related-paper">1.2 Related paper</h3>

<h4 id="submitted-paper">Submitted paper</h4>

<p><b>[2]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b> &amp; Kaber, D. B. (in review). Models of automation rate in human-in-the-loop systems and operator situation awareness responses. Submitted to IEEE Transactions on Human-Machine Systems (12/31/21).<br /><br />
<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9582630" target="_blank"><b>[C4]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>. and Kaber, D. Quantitative models for automation rate and situation awareness response: A case study of levels of driving automation, 2021 IEEE 2nd International Conference on Human-Machine Systems (ICHMS), 2021, pp. 1-6.</a></p>

<!-- ### 1.3 Demo video -->
<!-- ![](https://youtu.be/6xAK8W69i-g) -->]]></content><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><category term="markdown" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[During the operation of automated systems, if a user cannot accurately understand the structure and function of automation of the system, it is likely that distrust or over-trust in the automation will occur. To address this research gap, my dissertation research developed a continuous “automation rate” function to quantify levels of automation in complex systems. In addition, I proposed a new relationship between the AR function and operator situation awareness responses, based on existing empirical research findings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2. Roadway Signage for Novel Grade-separated Interchanges</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/GSIX.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2. Roadway Signage for Novel Grade-separated Interchanges" /><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/GSIX</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/GSIX.html"><![CDATA[<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
This is an NCDOT-funded project that used a driving simulator to compare the driving performance and mental state of young and middle-aged drivers while navigating standard intersections and novel GSI (contraflow and quadrant) conditions. The experiment also manipulated driver exposure to different configurations of lane assignment and decision point signs. 

</p>
</font>

<h3 id="21-project-overview">2.1 Project overview</h3>

<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
<!-- ## Here is a secondary heading -->
This study developed datasets on driver behavior in using novel interchange designs to support computational models for predicting performance with new designs and accelerating DOT interchange implementation.

<html>
    <head>

         <title>Changing Bullet Colors</title>

         <style>

             h3{

                 color:black;

             }

             ul{

                 list-style: none;

             }

             ul li::before {

                 /* \2022 is the CSS Code/unicode for a disc */

                 content: "\2022";  

                 color: inline-block; 

                 display: inline-block; 

                 width: 1em;

                 margin-left: -0.9em;

                 font-weight: bold;

                 font-size:0.5rem;

             }

         </style>

   </head>

   <body>

     My contributions in this project including:
     <ul>

         <li>Designed situation awareness queries to collect the situation awareness data of subjects at different interchanges and different signage configurations.</li>

         <li>Programmed Qualtrics surveys to render it in the desired format and convert output to spreadsheet file formats.</li>

         <li>Designed and conducted human factors experiment on effects of grade-separated interchange geometry and traffic control device design on driver visual behavior and performance.</li>

         <li>Post-processing and analysis of experimental data on subjects' situational awareness, mental load, driving performance, and eye trackers were performed using Python. In addition, descriptive and inferential statistical analyses were conducted on all these responses.</li>

         <li>Constructed four machine learning classification models to analyze and predict erroneous driver actions at novel interchange configurations given driver’s status. </li>

     </ul>

   </body>

</html>

</p>
</font>

<h4 id="ahfe-presentation-video"><a href="https://openaccess.cms-conferences.org/#/publications/book/978-1-958651-36-0/article/978-1-958651-36-0_32" target="_blank">AHFE</a> Presentation Video</h4>

<p align="center">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qTCoAUiOJkM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>

<h3 id="22-related-paper">2.2 Related paper</h3>
<h4 id="submitted-paper">Submitted paper</h4>
<p><b>[C1]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Kaber, D., Sabahi, S., and Cunningham, C. (2022; under review). Machine learning models of erroneous driver actions at novel interchange configurations, 2022 IEEE 3rd International Conference on Human-Machine Systems (ICHMS), 2022, pp. XX-XX.<br /></p>

<p><a href="https://openaccess.cms-conferences.org/#/publications/book/978-1-958651-36-0/article/978-1-958651-36-0_32" target="_blank"><b>[C3]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Pyo, K., Cunningham, C., Chase, T. and Kaber, D. Driver situation awareness and cognitive workload effects of novel interchange configurations and associated signage, 13th International Conference on Applied Human Factors and Ergonomics (AHFE), 2022; 60: 287-296. </a></p>

<h4 id="working-paper">Working paper</h4>
<p><b>[7]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Pyo, K., Cunningham, C., Chase, T. Kaber, D. Novel interchange configurations and associated signage assessment. Target journal: Applied Ergonomics.</p>

<h3 id="23-demo-video">2.3 Demo video</h3>

<!-- ![](https://youtu.be/db3A5tPrsq8) -->
<p align="center">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/db3A5tPrsq8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>]]></content><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><category term="markdown" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an NCDOT-funded project that used a driving simulator to compare the driving performance and mental state of young and middle-aged drivers while navigating standard intersections and novel GSI (contraflow and quadrant) conditions. The experiment also manipulated driver exposure to different configurations of lane assignment and decision point signs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">5. Other Projects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Other.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5. Other Projects" /><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Other</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/markdown/2019/09/01/Other.html"><![CDATA[<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
In addition to the above research studies, I have also been involved in other projects on systems safety analysis research, unmanned aerial vehicle interface design,consistency in the design of interchanges in high-density traffic corridors and non-safety-related in-vehicle and on-road message displays.  
</p>
</font>
<h3 id="51-systems-safety-analysis-research">5.1 Systems safety analysis research</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
Fault Tree Analysis (FTA) has realized substantial application for safety engineering; however, the method is not without limitations in comparison to other safety analysis techniques. Traditional FTA requires substantial time and effort even for single fault assessment including determining probability of occurrence. A constrained literature review and examination of functions available in commercial-off-the-shelf FTA software revealed current implementations to lack a structured functional approach to account for the severity of intermediate events to a fault as well as the severity of fault outcomes. To address this specific limitation, a novel Consequence Severity-Probability Importance Measure (CSPIM) is proposed for extension of static FTA. An algorithm is presented to achieve the CSPIM within FTA. In addition, we present a case study to make comparison of traditional FTA with the use of CSPIM within FTA. Results demonstrated that CSPIM effectively integrates a severity analysis feature in FTA and allows for risky events to be prioritized for safety controls, based on the measure.<br />
</p>
</font>

<h4 id="related-papers">Related papers</h4>
<p><b>[1]</b>. Kaber, D. B., <b>Liu, Y.</b> &amp; Lau, M. Y. (in processing). Considering Severity of Safety-Critical System Outcomes in Risk Analysis: An Extension of Fault-Tree Analysis. In J-C. Le Coze &amp; S. Antonsen, <i>SpringerBriefs in Safety Management - Safety in a Digital Age: Old and New Problems</i>. Cham, Switzerland: Springer.<br />
<b>[3]</b>. Lau, M., <b>Liu, Y.</b> &amp; Kaber, D. B. (in review). A consequence severity-probability importance measure for fault tree analysis. Submitted to <i>IEEE Transactions on Reliability Engineering</i> (9/24/21).</p>

<h3 id="52-unmanned-aerial-vehicle-interface-design">5.2 Unmanned aerial vehicle interface design</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAV) control interfaces is critical channel to transfer information from a vehicle to an operator. Existing research has heavily focused on increasing levels of vehicle automation but overlooked usable interface design as a method for system performance enhancement. This study investigated operator cognitive workload associated with different UAV interface design alternatives. Three control interface variations were generated and classified as “baseline”, “enhanced” usability and “degraded” usability. Physiological and subjective responses were collected as bases for workload response assessment under different task load conditions. Results on multiple response measures indicated that the “enhanced” interface produced the lowest operator workload and was robust to increased control task demands, as compared with the “baseline” and “degraded” interfaces. This research provides actionable guidelines for UAV control interface design. The approaches used in the study can be applied to interface evaluation for various types of UAVs, as well as other unmanned systems, towards improving human-automation interaction.<br />
</p>
</font>

<h4 id="related-papers-1">Related papers</h4>
<p><b>[4]</b>. Zhang, W., <b>Liu, Y.</b>  &amp; Kaber, D.B. (in revision). Effect of interface design on cognitive workload in unmanned aerial vehicle control. Second revision submitted to <i>Int. J. of Human Computer Studies</i> (4/12/21).</p>

<h3 id="53-consistency-in-the-design-of-interchanges-in-high-density-traffic-corridors">5.3 Consistency in the design of interchanges in high-density traffic corridors</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
This study addressed potential for driver errors in route selection when confronted with variations in interchange design in single roadway corridor as well as driver learning, adaptive and avoidance behaviors.<br />
</p>
</font>

<h4 id="related-papers-2">Related papers</h4>
<p><b>[8]</b>. <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Yang, G., Pyo, K., Cunningham, C., Chase, T., Kaber, D. B.. Design consistency. Target journal: <i>Applied Ergonomics</i>.</p>

<h3 id="54-non-safety-related-in-vehicle-and-on-road-message-displays">5.4 Non-safety-related in-vehicle and on-road message displays</h3>
<font size="3">
<p style="text-align:justify; text-justify:inter-ideograph;">
This study assessed effects of message content and format on driver visual behavior and vehicle control. <br /><br />Picture below displays of on-road signage (left panels) and invehicle display (right panels) for higher information load (upper panels) and lower information load (lower panels) conditions <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1071181320641472" target="_blank">[C5]</a>.<br />
</p>
</font>
<p><img src="/assets/images/banners/display.png" /></p>

<h4 id="related-papers-3">Related papers</h4>
<p><a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1071181320641472" target="_blank"><b>[C5]</b>. Cauffman, S.J., Deng, Y., <b>Liu, Y.</b>, Cunningham, C., Kaber, D. B. and Feng, J. Driver logo sign detection and hazard responses during partially automated driving. <i>Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Annual Meeting</i>. 2020; 64(1):1960-1964.</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Yunmei Liu</name></author><category term="markdown" /><category term="project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In addition to the above research studies, I have also been involved in other projects on systems safety analysis research, unmanned aerial vehicle interface design,consistency in the design of interchanges in high-density traffic corridors and non-safety-related in-vehicle and on-road message displays. 5.1 Systems safety analysis research Fault Tree Analysis (FTA) has realized substantial application for safety engineering; however, the method is not without limitations in comparison to other safety analysis techniques. Traditional FTA requires substantial time and effort even for single fault assessment including determining probability of occurrence. A constrained literature review and examination of functions available in commercial-off-the-shelf FTA software revealed current implementations to lack a structured functional approach to account for the severity of intermediate events to a fault as well as the severity of fault outcomes. To address this specific limitation, a novel Consequence Severity-Probability Importance Measure (CSPIM) is proposed for extension of static FTA. An algorithm is presented to achieve the CSPIM within FTA. In addition, we present a case study to make comparison of traditional FTA with the use of CSPIM within FTA. Results demonstrated that CSPIM effectively integrates a severity analysis feature in FTA and allows for risky events to be prioritized for safety controls, based on the measure.]]></summary></entry></feed>